Inventory of the John Marshall Papers 1771-1959
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
- Correspondence and Papers of John Marshall, Family Members and Other Individuals, 1771-1916, n.d. (Box 1-5)
  - Correspondence and Papers of John Marshall, 1771-1835, n.d., 269 items. (Box-folder 1-4)
    - Correspondence and Papers of John Marshall, 1830-1839., 55 items. (Box-folder 4:2)
      - Correspondence and Papers, 1830., 12 items. (Box-folder 4:2)
        - J[ohn] Marshall, Washington, [D.C.], to "Polly" [Mary Willis (Ambler) Marshall], Richmond, Virginia, 31 January 1830., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 4:2)
          Writes of his son Edward [C. Marshall] who is a proud new father; dined with the President [Andrew Jackson] and his [Andrew Jackson's] niece Mrs. [Andrew Jackson] [Emily] Donelson; saw Tom Francis a week ago; Judges [William] Johnson and [John] McLean do not board with the other judges; Judge [Smith] Thompson is sick; complains about not receiving his rent from his tenants Mr. [?] Sprigg on the Potomac and another at Anderson's Bottoms.
        - J[ohn] Marshall, Washington, [D.C.], to "Polly" [Mary Willis (Ambler) Marshall], Richmond, Virginia, 14 February 1830., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 4:2)
          Discusses the dinner parties which he and his brother Justices have attended; the Secretary of State [Martin van Buren] gave one for the new bride of the President's [Andrew Jackson's] nephew [?]; he dined yesterday with the British Minister; the influenza is as prevalent as it was in Richmond; Judge [Gabriel] Duval left town because of a relapse of his son; James [Kieth Marshall, his son] wrote three days past about his brother Edward [Carrington Marshall]; mentions Washington's Birthday Celebrations effect on her.
          Including Pst of ALS. 3 pages. Including TCy of ALS. 2 pages.
        - J[ohn] Marshall, Washington, [D.C.], to "Polly" [Mary Willis (Ambler) Marshall], Richmond, Virginia, 28 February 1830., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 4:2)
          Heard from his granddaughter that she [Mary Willis Ambler Marshall] became indisposed upon her return from Chickahominy; has received a letter from his son James who sold his horse for $l000[?]; Mr. [Joseph] Story, who has been laid up for a week under the doctor's hand has returned to court.
        - J[ohn] Marshall, Washington, [D.C.], to "Polly" [Mary Willis (Ambler) Marshall], Richmond, Virginia, 7 March [1830?]., 3 pages. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 4:2)
          Discusses his morning routine; dined yesterday with Mr. [?] Swann; Mr. [Joseph] Story is still not well enough to go out; talked about his nephew William [?] with Mr. [?] Mercer; Tom Francis took a stage for Kentucky; saw Mr. [?] Coleman, husband of his niece Lucy [?], who is a strong Jackson man; his [John Marshall's] nephew Tom [Marshall] son of Humphry [Marshall] is a strong Clay man, and will oppose Mr. Coleman in the next Congressional election; party plays havoc with the Kentucky part of his [John Marshall's] family.
        - John L. Tillinghast, Washington, [D.C.], to [the Supreme Court, Washington, D.C.], 17 March 1830., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 4:2)
          Encloses papers which Mr. [Francis Scott] Key could not present to the Court in person.
        - [Thomas H.] Benton, [Washington, D.C.] to [John Marshall, Washington, D.C.], "Saturday, afternoon" [ca. March 1830]., 1 page. AL. (Box-folder 4:2)
          Sends his respects to the Chief Justice; makes arrangements to see him.
        - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to Humphrey Marshall, near Frankfort, Kentucky, 4 April 1830., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 4:2)
          Discusses arrangements to have his father's [Thomas Marshall] will proved in the Virginia General Court so they can rule on his [Revolutionary War?] claim for half pay.
          Including Pst. of ALS. 2 pages.
        - [John Marshall], Richmond, [Virginia], to Edward C[arrington] Marshall, "Carrington," near Oak Hill, Fauquier [County, Virginia], 22 May 1830., 3 pages. Pst of ALS. Incomplete, torn. (Box-folder 4:2)
          Discusses land transactions with Capt. Slaughter and Major Thompsons; mentions Mr. [?] John Lewis's sale of his slaves to pay off Warner Lewis's debts; discusses their financial difficulties with Mr. [?] Nicholas and Mr. [?] Smith; encloses a promissory note of Edward C. and Mary Nelson Marshall on the Farmers Bank of Virginia for $5000.
        - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to James Hillhouse, Washington, District of Columbia, 26 May 1830., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 4:2)
          Discusses his [James Hillhouse] 1808 proposal of electing the president by drawing straws among Senators; he [John Marshall] was opposed to it in the past, but has seen too much strife and bitterness in party politics.
        - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to Joseph Story, Cambridge, Massachusetts, 15 October 1830., 3 pages. TCy of ALS. (Box-folder 4:2)
          Thanks him for sending a sermon on the late Massachusetts Chief Justice [Isaac Parker] and his [Joseph Story's] own sketch of Parker's Character; thanks him also for a box of fish; is sorry that brother Justice [John] McLean could not acquiesce in the [Craig V.] Missouri case; is-chagrined that so many cases, including Soulard, Smith and Cathcart and Robertson, were left incomplete at their last setting; discusses Mr. [James] Madison's letter to the editor of the North American Review.
        - J[ohn] Marshall, [Richmond, Virginia?], to Crittenden Lyon, [n.p.], 26 December 1830., 1 page. TCy of ALS. (Box-folder 4:2)
          Letter of reference for Capt. [?] Baylis who served with him during the Revolution.
      - Correspondence and Papers, 1831., 15 items. (Box-folder 4:2)
        - J[ohn] Marshall, Washington, [D.C.], to "Polly" [Mary Willis (Ambler) Marshall], Richmond, Virginia, 30 January 1831., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 4:3)
          Heard from Colo.[nel] [?] Lambert that she was in her usual health; discusses the latest snowfall; dined with the minister of France and his wife, neither of whom could speak English; dined with Secretary of State Martin van Buren yesterday; saw Mr. [?] Robinson yesterday who gave news of his [John Marshall's] sister [Elizabeth] Colston and her family.
        - J[ohn] Marshall, Washington, [D.C.], to "Polly" [Mary Willis (Ambler) Marshall], Richmond, Virginia, 7 February 1831., 3 pages. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 4:3)
          Enjoyed calling on Mrs. [?] Sedgwick author of Hope Leslie today; the snow and ice has interrupted regular mail delivery from Richmond; they have lost their Marshal [?] Ringold, whose being ousted from office will distress his family.
          On verso, J[ohn] Marshall to [Edward Carrington Marshall]. Asks him to find a valuable 1776 English pamphlet on the Declaration of Independence which Mr. [?] Storrs lent him [John Marshall] and which he misplaced.
        - [John Marshall], Richmond, [Virginia]. Poem, "Lines written for a lady's Album," 30 March 1831. (Box-folder 4:3)
        - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to Joseph Story, Cambridge near Boston, [Massachusetts], 3 May 1831., 3 pages. TCy of ALS. (Box-folder 4:3)
          Sent him a barrel of hams on the schooner King to be deposited with Fisher and Pewer of Boston; asks him what the "wise men in the East" think of the Cabinet upheaval; discusses arrangements for new quarters in Washington as the Justices will no longer be lodging with Mr. [?] Brown; discusses the copy of Algernon Sianey ["Letters.. .in Defence of Civil Liberty and against the Encroachments of Military Despotism"?] which he [John Marshall] sent him [Joseph Story] earlier; discusses possibility of war and the reform in Great Britain; will set out on his circuit at the end of the week.
        - J[ohn] Marshall, Raleigh, [North Carolina], to "Polly" [Mary Willis (Ambler) Marshall], Richmond, Virginia, 12 May 1831., 3 pages. Pst of ALs. (Box-folder 4:3)
          Arrived yesterday; thanks her for the cushion she made him to ease his journey; discusses the visit of a niece.
        - Joseph Story, Cambridge, [Massachusetts], to John Marshall, Richmond, Virginia, 29 May 1831., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 4:3)
          Received his letter and hams; regrets that the Court is moving out of Mr. brown's; would like to lodge with him [John Marshall] and Judge Thompson; discusses the break-up of the cabinet, which was a surprise to him; thanks him for the Algernon Sidney pamphlet; informs him of the death of his [Joseph Story's] 10 year old daughter.
        - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to Joseph Story, Cambridge, Massachusetts, 26 June 1831., 5 pages. TCy of ALS. (Box-folder 4:3)
          Received his letters of May 25 and 31 and adopted his opinions respecting admiralty jurisdiction; discusses arrangements for lodgings in Washington next winter and explains why he cannot do anything till he hears from Judge [Henry] Baldwin; sympathizes with him over the loss of his child; tells of his similar experiences; he also wrote a poem in the occasion of his child's death, which he would have enclosed, but it was lost.
        - J[ohn] Q[uincy] Adams, Quincy, [Massachusetts], to John Marshall, Richmond, Virginia, 17 September 1831., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 4:3)
          Thanks him for his letter of 9 September; has conversed with Judge [Joseph] Story about the Declaration of Independence; discusses his [John Quincy Adams] ideas about it and the constitutional principles of state sovereignty, secession, and nullification.
        - J[ohn] Marshall, Philadelphia, [Pennsylvania], to "Polly" [Nary Willis (Ambler) Marshall], Richmond, Virginia, 6 October 1831., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 4:3)
          Discusses his medical examination by Doctor [Philip Syng] Physick; will probably not see her again till he rides the circuit court 22 November; the gentlemen of the city, especially those of the bar, are painfully solicitous to show their respect; Nr.[?] Peters and Dr. [?] Gillespie press him to stay with them; gives directions for his crops to be tended to.
        - J[ohn] Marshall, Philadelphia, [Pennsylvania], to "Polly" [Mary Willis (Ambler) Marshall, Richmond, Virginia], 12 October 1831., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 4:3)
          The rains of the last several days have prevented Dr. [Philip Syng] Physick from operating; discusses preparations for his medical treatment; missed Cary Ambler's visit because he was sitting for a portrait; Edward Ambler is in town; received a letter from brother [Joseph] Story; mentions his diet.
        - J[ohn] Marshall, Philadelphia, [Pennsylvania], to Joseph Story, Cambridge, Massachusetts, 12 October 1831., 4 pages. TCy of ALS. (Box-folder 4:3)
          Discusses his medical treatment and Doctor [Philip Syng] Physick; Brother [Justice Henry] Baldwin is here; discusses the arrangements for the Justices' lodgings in Washington, either at Mrs. [?] Peyton's or Mr. [?] Peters'; explains why he did not think he would serve on the court at its next session; discusses his health and ailments of the past summer.
        - J[ohn] Marshall, Philadelphia, [Pennsylvania], to James K. Marshall, "Moreland," Fauquier County, Virginia, 12 October 1831., 2 pages. Cy of ALS. (Box-folder 4:3)
          Mr. [?] Giles will give news of his health; describes his ailment ("stones in the bladder") and the Doctor's examination; his operation by Doctor [Philip Syng] Physick has been delayed because of the weather; describes the Doctor and his [John Marshall's] accommodations; tell Major [?] Ambler that his brothers Edward and Cary are in town.
        - Edward Everett, Charlestown, [Massachusetts], to John Marshall, Philadelphia, [Pennsylvania], 18 October 1831., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 4:3)
          Heard of and congratulates him on successful operation; regards his health as "a matter of the highest national concernment..."
          On verso, [John Marshall, to Edward Everett], incomplete. Is flattered by his kina token; describes his tedious operation; thanks him for his letter.
        - J[ohn] Marshall, Philadelphia, [Pennsylvania], to Joseph Story, Cambridge, Massachusetts, 10 November 1831., 3 pages. TCy of ALS. (Box-folder 4:3)
          Learned from Mr. [?] Peters that he was seriously indisposed; intends to leave for Richmond next week; discusses difficulties in their living arrangements; they will probably quarter with [?] Ringold; Mr. [William] Johnson will live by himself, and [John] McLean will preserve his former position; Brother [Henry] Baldwin presides over the circuit court in session now in Philadelphia; describes his [John Marshall's] operation and medicine.
        - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to James [Markham] Marshall, Happy Creek, Frederick, near Front Royal, [Virginia], 19 December 1831., 3 pages. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 4:3)
          Discusses the latest legal difficulties involving the Fairfax lands; his wife [Mary Willis (Ambler) Marshall] lies at death's door.
          Including TCy of ALS. 3 pages.
      - Correspondence and Papers, 1832., 12 items. (Box-folder 4:4)
        - J[ohn] Marshall, Washington [D.C.], to Henry Lee, [Washington, D.C.?], 29 January 1832., 3 pages. TCy of ALS. (Box-folder 4:4)
          Discusses a pamphlet to which he [Henry Lee] alluded in his letter; mentions [Thomas] Jefferson's"unjustifiable aspersions" on his [John Marshall's] conduct and principles; writes of his own and [George] Logon's experiences with the Revolutionary government of France; mentions the journal he kept in Paris.
          Original is located in the Marshall Papers,
        - Legal opinion delivered by John Marshall in the case of Stephen Sicara et al. vs. Nancy Davis et al, [January 1832]., 1 page. Pst of AD. Incomplete. (Box-folder 4:4)
          Library of U.S. Supreme Court, Washington D.C.
        - Will of John Marshall with Codicils dated 1832-1835, 9 April 1832. (Box-folder 4:4)
          Certificate of the Clerk of the Circuit Court of Fauquier County dated 16 March 1961.
          Fauquier County Courthouse?
        - J[ohn] Marshall, Carrington, Fauquier County, Virginia, to Mary [(Marshall)] Harvie, Richmond, [Virginia], 22 April 1832., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 4:4)
          Makes arrangements for the sale of Edward's [Carrington Marshall's] bank shares; her brother Tom [Thomas Marshall] tears that he will not win his election because he raises the clerk's fees.
        - Richard Henry Wilde, Washington, [D.C.], to John Marshall, Richmond, Virginia, 18 June 1832., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 4:4)
          He was gratified by his complimentary comments on the speech he [Richard Henry Wilde] sent him [John Marshall]; sends him Mr. [?] Ingham's report on the relative value of gold and silver and Mr. [?] White's reports on coins; mentions Mr. [?] Jacob's work on the subject.
        - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia] to Joseph Story, Cambridge, Massachusetts, 2 August 1832., 4 pages. TCy of ALS. (Box-folder 4:4)
          Thanks him for sending him the first volume of the American Library of Useful Knowledge; the Librarian of Congress has asked him [John Marshall] to help spend $5000 on law books for the library, and he [John Marshall] asks him [Joseph Story] to suggest titles; discusses [Charles] Mercer and the Bank Question and internal improvements in Virginia; the party guide The Enquirer is unable to make Mr. [John] Barbour"pull in the traces;" discusses national politics and the threat of nullification; comments upon the Cholera epidemics in the seaports of New York and Boston.
        - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to [?, n.p.], 12 September 1832., 1 page. Pst of PL. (Box-folder 4:4)
          Has received and read his essay A Congress of Nations for the Amicable Adjustments of National Differences; Feels that its argument is well arranged and supported by applicable biblical quotations, but is also impracticable.
          See the November and December 1832 issue of The Comet.
        - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to [James Keith Marshall, "Moreland", Fauquier County, Virginia], 15 September 1832., 1 page. TCy of ALS. (Box-folder 4:4)
          Is having difficulties selling his stock for him; there is a severe outbreak of cholera in Richmond; discusses the disease; is relieved to hear that he is restored to health and that John Harvie is getting better; discusses the disabling of his horse.
        - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to Joseph Story, Cambridge, Massachusetts, 22 September 1832., 3 pages. TCy of ALS. (Box-folder 4:4)
          Thanks him for his help in selecting titles for the congressional law library; discusses his choice of books; is gratified that his course on constitutional law [at Harvard] nears completion; shares his gloomy prospects of the country; "The case of the south seems to me to be desperate.. .The union has been prolonged thus far by miracles. I fear they cannot continue."
        - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to James K[eith] Marshall, Leeds Manor [illegible], Fauquier [County, Virginia], 8 October 1832., 2 pages. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 4:4)
          Discusses how he sold his [James Keith Marshall's] and Edward's [Carrington Marshall's] stock; hopes his merchandising speculation will be successful; congratulates him on the birth of his daughter; has just returned from Mr. White's son's funeral, who died of cholera; discusses the disease.
        - Memorial written by John Marshall to his wife Mary Willis (Ambler) Marshall on the first anniversary of her death in which he quotes a poetic lament written by Gen[eral John] Burgoyne, 25 December 1832., 4 pages. Pst of AM. (Box-folder 4:4)
        - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to Joseph Story, Cambridge, Massachusetts, 25 December 1832., 5 pages. TCy of ALS. (Box-folder 4:4)
          Thanks him for the dedication of his new book; congratulates him upon its completion; the [Virginia] legislature is in session; discusses Andrew Jackson's response to nullification and his party's reaction to it; writes of Virginia's relationship to South Carolina and the possibility of their joining in a southern confederacy; thanks him for a copy of Mr. [Daniel] Webster's speech; mentions Brother Justice [Henry] Baldwin's sickness.
      - Thomas A. Marshall, Washington, [D.C.], to John Marshall, Richmond, Virginia, 4 January 1833., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 4:5)
        Encloses a power of attorney authorizing him to draw what is coming to him [Thomas A. Marshall] on account of grandfather's [Col. Thomas Marshall] halt pay; discusses Congress and the Nullification crisis; mentions Judge [Henry] Baldwin's misfortune and that Judge [Smith] Thompson is in town.
        Including ADS. 2 pages. 3 January 1833. Power of attorney granting John Marshall the right to draw the money due Thomas A. Marshall as heir to Colonel Thomas Marshall, Revolutionary War veteran entitled to the half pay pension; signed by Justice of the Peace D.A. Hall.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Washington, [D.C.], to [?, n.p.], 5 February 1833., 1 page. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 4:5)
        Returns his portfolio of drawings of Washington and pictures of Revolutionary Boston; recalls traveling to Richmond with him once.
        Illinois State Historical Library, Springfield, Illinois.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Washington, [D.C.] to Jaquelin B. Harvie, Richmond, Virginia, 8 February 1833., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 4:5)
        Informs him that his son was accepted to West Point; does not think the Tariff bill or the bill concerning South Carolina's legislature will pass Congress.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to Charles Carter, n.p., 8 May 1833., 2 pages. TCy of ALS. (Box-folder 4:5)
        Received his letter of 27 April; discusses Mr. [Edmund] Pendleton; mentions a copy of a letter from Mr. Carr in the possession of Col. John Nichols; Augustine Davis may have published it; his [Charles Carter's] brother has written to Mr. [?] Sujt in regards to it; discusses Mr. [Edmund] Pendleton, [Thomas] Jefferson, and the XYZ dispatch.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to Joseph Story, Cambridge, Massachusetts, 3 June 1833., 3 pages. TCy of ALS. (Box-folder 4:5)
        Discusses Lt. Randolph's case, Mr. Watkin's case, the power of arrest, and the Judiciary Act; rejoices at the abridgement of his Commentaries for the public; discusses its place in colleges and universities.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to Henry Lee, Paris, [France], 21 September l833[?]., 3 pages. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 4:5)
        Discusses the national fervor in France based upon the martial glory of Napoleon and demonstrated by the statue at the top of the column of Austerlitz in the Place de Vendome; compares Napoleon's popularity with the people to that of George Washington's, Hannibal's, and Ceasar's; all were "victims of the infernal machine" [party politics]; discusses national politics and [Martin] Van Buren.
        Duke University, Durham, North Carolina.
      - Thomas Marshall, Oak Hill, [Fauquier County, Virginia], to John Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], 29 October 1833., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 4:5)
        Discusses the addition James [K. Marshall] is making to the house at Leeds for his father [John Marshall]; mentions Jaquelin's [Marshall] experiences of housing slaves in basements at Prospect Hill; mentions the weather and growth of crops and the health of his [Thomas Marshall's] daughter Mary; Aunt [Elizabeth (Marshall)] Colston is in poor health and will probably not visit Richmond this Winter; his [Thomas Marshall's] son John's plans have changed and he has bought Mr. [?] Smith's tract of land; tell Mr. [?] Tiffin that the girls have never received the box of articles he sent to Mr. [?] Cawood by steamboat.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond,[Virginia], to Joseph Story, Cambridge near Boston, [Massachusetts], 16 November 1833., 5 pages. TCy of ALS. (Box-folder 4:5)
        Has just received a letter from Mr. [?] Ringold who has moved from Washington and can not accommodate them next winter; "the political world.., is surely moved topsy turvy;" mentions southern states insistence on state sovereignty; asks him about Brother [Justice John?] McClain [McLean's?] opinion in Tennessee.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Jr. Winchester, [Virginia], to "Uncle" John Marshall, Richmond, Virginia, 16 March 1834., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 4:5)
        Discusses the 1793 contract signed with Denny Fairfax for the Manor of Leeds and the South Branch Manor; suggests strategies to prove their legal title to the land.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to James K. Marshall, Manor of Leeds, Fauquier [County, Virginia], 12 April 1834., 2 pages. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 4:5)
        Discusses the purchase of land and the legalities it would entail; mentions the possibility of mortgaging the Mont Blanc estate for a loan.
        John Marshall House, Virginia State Library.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to Joseph Story, Cambridge, Massachusetts, 24 April 1834., 5 pages. TCy of ALS. (Box-folder 4:5)
        His present, a copy of his Commentaries[on the Constitution] and Allison's Sermons, has arrived on the Lucy and Abigail; has sent him copies of his [John Marshall's] Life of Washington to be delivered to [Daniel] Webster, [John Quincy] Adams; the Massachusetts Historical Society, the Boston Athanaeum (which complimented him by having his portrait painted for their gallery), and Mrs. [?] Ledyard; discusses publication of his [Joseph Story's] Commentaries, which will not be popular in the South; discusses [Henry] Clay's Tariff bill.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to James K. Marshall, Leeds Manor, Fauquier [County, Virginia], 9 May 1834., 2 pages. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 4:5)